## Zheng Gao

CONTACT Information Applied Scientist Amazon Alexa AI

Seattle, WA

(412)638-3401 zhenggao@amazon.com https://zhenggao.io

RESEARCH Interest My research interests are primarily in the area of Graph Mining and Natural Language Processing (NLP). Particularly, I am applying deep learning techniques on their interdisciplinary field therein to solve Community Detection, Information Retrieval and Recommendation related tasks.

SKILL

- Languages: Python, Java, SQL, Shell, LATEX
- Tools: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Spark, Maven, Lucene, MySQL, MongoDB, Neo4j

**EDUCATION** 

Indiana University Bloomington, United States

08/2015 - 06/2020

**Ph.D.** in Information Science, Advisor: Xiaozhong Liu

• Minor in Computer Science, Advisor: Xiaofeng Wang

University of Pittsburgh, United States

08/2013 - 05/2015

M.S. in Information Science

Shanghai International Studies University, China

08/2009 - 05/2013

**B.S.** in Information Management and System

Industry Experience

### Applied Scientist II, Alexa AI, Amazon

06/2020 - now

• Built a DownStream Impact (DSI) framework to estimate the effect of Alexa Intelligence Decision programs on future engagement, revenue, and contribution to profit.

#### Data Scientist Intern, Alexa AI, Amazon

06/2019 - 09/2019

- Applied deep language models (i.e. Bert, ELMo) and state-of-art clustering methods to extract
  influential text patterns from user requests, which entirely replaced the existing human manual
  interpretation on annotated datasets.
- Built up an automatic pipeline by Spark and Shell scripts to enable training models on multiple data resources (i.e. Amazon S3 and Redshift) under Alexa restricted environment.

#### Research Intern, DAMO Academy / AI Lab, Alibaba

02/2018 - 03/2019

- Generated product review summary from user consecutive behaviors by leveraging dynamic matrix factorization, deep reinforcement learning (Policy Gradient) and sequence to sequence model (Neural Machine Translation) with Attention techniques.
- Proposed an end-to-end pairwise ranking model with transfer learning techniques to detect communities in targeted sparse graphs.
- Detected multilevel anomalies from high dimensional dynamic use logs via Adversarial Autoencoder and Attention-based hierarchical representation learning.

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Indiana University Bloomington

#### Instructor / Lecturer

• ILS-Z534: Search (Spring/Fall 2018, Spring/Fall 2019)

#### Associate Instructor

- ILS-Z534: Search (Fall 2015, Fall 2016, Fall 2017, Spring 2020)
- INFO-I590: Topics in Informatics (Summer 2016, Spring/Summer 2017)

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Zheng Gao**, Hongsong Li, Zhuoren Jiang, Xiaozhong Liu. Detecting User Community in Sparse Domain via Cross-Graph Pairwise Learning. *ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR)*, 2020.
- [2] **Zheng Gao**, Lujun Zhao, Heng Huang, Hongsong Li, Changlong Sun, Luo Si, Xiaozhong Liu. Behavior based Dynamic Summarization on Product Aspects via Reinforcement Neighbour Selection. *European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI)*, 2020.

- [3] Zhuoren Jiang, **Zheng Gao**, Jinjiong Lan, Hongxia Yang, Yao Lu and Xiaozhong Liu. Task-Oriented Genetic Activation for Large-Scale Complex Heterogeneous Graph Embedding. The Web Conference (WWW), 2020.
- [4] Zheng Gao, Chun Guo, Xiaozhong Liu. Efficient Personalized Community Detection via Genetic Evolution. The Genetic and Evolutionary Computation Conference (GECCO), 2019.
- [5] Zheng Gao, Gang Fu, Chunping Ouyang, Satoshi Tsutsui, Xiaozhong Liu, Jeremy Yang, Christopher Gessner, Brian Foote, David Wild, Ying Ding, Qi Yu. edge2vec: Representation Learning Using Edge Semantics for Biomedical Knowledge Discovery. BMC Bioinformatics, 2019. (impact factor = 2.511).
- [6] Yongzhen Wang, Xiaozhong Liu, Zheng Gao. Neural Related Work Summarization with a Joint Context-driven Attention Mechanism. Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), 2018.
- [7] Zizhe Gao, Zheng Gao, Heng Huang, Zhuoren Jiang, Yuliang Yan. An End-to-end Model of Predicting Diverse Ranking On Heterogeneous Feeds. eCOM Workshop at ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (eCom-SIGIR), 2018.
- [8] Zheng Gao, Lin Guo, Chi Ma, Xiao Ma, Kai Sun, Hang Xiang, Xiaoqiang Zhu, Hongsong Li, Xiaozhong Liu. AMAD: Adversarial Multiscale Anomaly Detection on High-Dimensional and Time-Evolving Categorical Data. Deep Learning Practice for High-Dimensional Sparse Data Workshop at ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (DLP-KDD), 2019.
- [9] Zhuoren Jiang, Liangcai Gao, Ke Yuan, **Zheng Gao**, Zhi Tang, Xiaozhong Liu. Mathematics Content Understanding for Cyberlearning via Formula Evolution Map. ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management (CIKM), 2018.
- [10] Xiaozhong Liu, Xing Yu, Zheng Gao, Tian Xia, Johan Bollen. Comparing Community-based Information Adoption and Diffusion across Different Microblogging Sites. ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media, 2016.
- [11] Zheng Gao, Vincent Malic, Shutian Ma, Patrick Shih. How to Make a Successful Movie: Factor Analysis from both Financial and Critical Perspectives. International Conference on Information, 2019.
- [12] Yongzhen Wang, Yan Lin, **Zheng Gao**, Yan Chen. A Two-stage Iterative Approach to Improve Crowdsourcing-based Relevance Assessment. Arabian Journal for Science and Engineering, 2019.
- [13] Zheng Gao, John Wolohan, Fast NLP-based Pattern Matching in Real Time Tweet Recommendation. Text REtrieval Conference (TREC), 2017.
- [14] Zheng Gao, Rui Bi. University of Pittsburgh at TREC 2014 Microblog Track. Text REtrieval Conference (TREC), 2014.
- [15] Zheng Gao, Xiaozhong Liu. Personalized Community Detection in Scholarly Network. International Conference on Information, 2017.
- [16] Tian Xia, Xing Yu, Zheng Gao, Yijun Gu, Xiaozhong Liu. Internal/External Information Access and Information Diffusion in Social Media. International Conference on Information, 2017.
- [17] Nan Li, Naren Suri, Zheng Gao, Tian Xia, Xiaozhong Liu, Katy Borner. Enter a Job, Get Course Recommendations. International Conference on Information, 2017.

#### SERVICE Conference Reviewer & PC Member

- The Web Conference (WWW 2018, 2019, 2020)
- ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR 2018)
- ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining Workshops (DLP-KDD 2020, IWKG-KDD 2020)

#### Journal Reviewer

- Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology (JASIST 2018, 2019)
- BMC Bioinformatics (2019, 2020)
- Social Network Analysis and Mining (SNAM 2018, 2019, 2020)
- Medical Science Monitor (2019)
- Tung-li Yuan Memorial Fellowship, Indiana University Bloomington
  - Clayton A. Shepherd Scholarship, Indiana University Bloomington

AWARD